Good evening everyone. I'll now call to
order this September 9th meeting of
Lancaster City Council. Welcome. Uh a
couple reminders here at the top of the
meeting before we begin. This meeting
and its participants are being recorded
this evening and do please take a moment
to silence your phones and devices if
you haven't done so already. I'll make
one note about the agenda. Resolution
number 63 um is not being taken up this
evening. It will appear on our agenda
for the 23rd of September. So, at our
next regular meeting, during our meeting
this evening, there will be
opportunities for public comment. The
first general public comment period is
for residents that have registered in
advance for the opportunity to speak
about items not on the agenda. Residents
may also comment on individual items on
our legislative legislative agenda.
That's item nine in front of us tonight.
Finally, a second public comment period
will be at the end of the agenda for
anyone wishing to speak uh to address
council about items not on the agenda.
All other speakers will be reminded all
speakers rather will be reminded to
begin with your name and block of
residence for our meeting record um and
address their comments toward council.
Please be advised that public comment is
not a question and answer period. All
comments are limited to three minutes
per speaker. And to keep time, there
will be a light in front of me that
turns green when a speaker begins. It
will blink yellow when there is one
minute remaining and blink red when
three minutes has been expended. At the
end of three minutes, uh the speaker
will be asked to end their comment. I
appreciate everyone's cooperation uh to
maintain order and equal time and also
remind speakers and everyone in the room
that members of the audience will be uh
and council are expected to conduct
themselves in an orderly manner and
remain respectful to others. Thank you.
And now for all of those who are willing
and able, please rise for the pledge of
allegiance.
>> I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for it stands. Nation under
God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Mr. Harris, would you please call the
role of members this evening?
>> Yes, Madam President.
>> Mr. Matt
>> here.
>> Mr. Royo
>> Mr. Cle
>> here.
>> Miss Craig
>> Miss Diaz.
>> Mr. Harsh
>> here.
>> And President B
>> here. Council Diaz is excused this
evening.
Uh our next item is the approval of the
minutes of the August 26, 2025 uh
meeting of council.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second.
Counselors, are there are there any
comments on the meeting minutes?
>> Hearing none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Med
>> I.
>> Mr. Roya.
>> I
>> Mr. Please.
>> I Miss Craig
>> I
and President Baker
>> I.
>> We'll move into proclamations, honors,
awards, and resolutions of recognition
this evening. We begin with council
resolution number 56, 2025. Mr. Harris.
>> A resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster recognizing welcoming week
in the city of Lancaster and celebrating
the city's continuing designation as a
certified welcoming city by the
organization Welcoming America.
>> Motion to approve. Second.
>> We have a motion and a second.
Councilors, thank you very much for
allowing me to introduce this this
evening. Uh tonight we have uh Zyra Fulu
uh from the city of Lancaster who will
be speaking to our efforts uh
maintaining our welcoming city status
and the events that we have uh for
welcoming week
or perhaps we have Millsy Krosco.
We welcome you. Uh you can use uh either
one of the mics there. Thank you. And
you may just have to turn it on with the
button. Thank you for joining us.
Yeah, push the button.
>> Oh,
>> you got it.
>> Here we go.
>> Okay, great. Thank you everyone. Um, I
will be providing uh an update on the
office of language services which uh
supports the certifi and is required by
the certified um welcoming certification
uh and also supports our diverse
community members.
So again, um good evening council
members and mayor Sarashi. Uh thank you
for the opportunity to present another
uh update from the office of language
services. Um
I am here to share our mission, our work
and why it is uh critical to ensuring
equitable access to city services for
all our residents. Um next slide,
please. Our
mission is clear. We are dedicated to
ensuring that all residents have equal
access to city services regardless of
the language they speak. To achieve this
mission, we provide three core core
services. Translation services,
interpretation services, language
support and consulting. Uh some service
highlights over the past eight months
are uh we have supported 25 initiatives
in person uh community engagements
whether by personally attending the
events or meetings or by sending an
inerson interpreter. We have translated
more than a 100 documents, social media
posts and flyers, fostered cultural
group connections with public safety and
other departments. provided uh staff
training and provided language access
consultation for department initiatives
have access sensors uh local language
demographics and survey staff for
language access improvement. Uh next
slide please
the right there. Thank you. And so um
this slide uh is a snapshot of all the
city uh community engagement supported
by language access as part of the done
um department of neighborhood engagement
and part of the engagement team.
Language access also uh provides uh
supports as uh the city team um goes to
events and engages uh in city
initiatives through community partner
events and meetings. Uh some of the
events for example have been uh ASL
interpretations at um Celebrate
Lancaster to like uh supporting the team
members at the African-American cultural
affair as they were tableabling and
providing um engagement to the community
at the events and many more than 25
events that I have attended or
supported.
Uh next slide please.
Uh slide four provides appropriate
analytics comparison of 2023 and 2024
highlighting an increase in usage by
year as staff receive training and
become more acquainted with language
access tools and services. Next slide
please.
And here is um this slide provides a
glance at department propio language
line usage. Uh the 2025 propio one
platform usage uh rema remains strong
and is increasing and those statistics
will be provided in uh 2026 once the
year 2025 is over and we collect all the
data. As you may observe, uh, our police
department, uh, continues to utilize,
uh, as the department that uses us the
most among many all the other
departments that are using our language
uh, line services. And I would like to
take uh a moment to acknowledge and
thank all city department staff
including the police the police baru for
having a dedicated heart to serving our
multicultural community with dignity and
respect without regard of what language
a person may speak. It truly embodies
the city's core values of quality,
teamwork, integrity, and respect. Thank
you for being champions of language
access and for upholding the values that
make our communities stronger together.
Next slide, please.
Why are we doing this work?
Um, the Office of Language Services has
conducted assessments to understand the
population being served. Here are some
preliminary census findings
from for example language spoken at
home. Um it highlights that 34.8% of
households speak a language other than
English at home.
In comparison to the actual lan larger
area of Lancaster County and even the
state of Pennsylvania, uh the city of
Lancaster remains with a very uh diverse
community.
In addition, uh 40 28.80%
of households speak Spanish at home. And
of the 28%,
45.8% of the Spanish speaking population
is limited English proficient. We also
serve several small language communities
such as Swahili, Arabic, Haitian Creole
and over 23 languages represented as
requested languages within our language
line which have very high limited
English uh proficient percentages
often lacking access to adequate
language support um because the the
languages are limited um of limited
diffusion and there's less community
members to support each other also 57
countries are represented um in the city
through places of birth.
Next slide please.
Therefore uh the office of language
services launched a staff survey to
receive feedback on the services and
tools being provided to staff to improve
services. We have not received the
official report. However, I am sharing
preliminary survey results with you. Uh
77% of participants, staff participants
are aware of language services and
report use of propio and leverage
bilingual staff highlighting the
importance of uh training our bilingual
staff. 45% of participants are facing
challenges and to better serve have
requested supports in training with
scenarios, quick reference guides, basic
language phrases among other requests.
In conclusion, some trends from our
preliminary findings are a need to
increase bilingual staff training,
evaluate new language access
technologies,
and evaluate um elevate communications
among staff
and thank you for this uh opportunity to
provide this update on the language
office of language services. Uh in
addition to that, in celebration of uh
welcoming week, um the city of Lancaster
has uh the welcoming week uh lineup of
events
uh that began last Friday with
international first Friday and continues
throughout the week um through September
17th.
Any comments, questions?
>> Thank you so much for your presentation
this evening and highlighting the work
of the language access program. It's
really vital to ensuring that everyone
has access to city services. Um, and
just excited to welcome uh uh recognize
welcoming week September 12th through
the 21st. Councilors, any questions or
comments?
>> Councelor Amed.
>> Thank you, Council President. Thank you
for the presentation. I just wanted to
take the time to thank the
administration and the Department of
Neighborhood Engagement for continuing
to work uh even during times of
challenges, uncertainty, continuing to
work with our many community partners uh
to sure that we continue to celebrate
our commitment to welcoming and
diversity here in the city of Lancaster
and um language access um uh initiatives
show how we can continue those um uh
intentional services and make sure that
everybody has a dignified experience
here in the city of L. So, I just wanted
to take that time to thank you all.
>> Thank you. Other council comments,
>> council president,
>> council hir.
>> Uh, thank you, Zyra, for the
presentation. Um, thank you for all of
the tremendous work, uh, that you and
your department are doing. Um, it's
really important. I, if I understood the
one statistic on the one slide
correctly, you said that 34.8% of people
are speaking a language other than
English at home. I mean, I think we just
ought to put that in perspective. That
means one in every three people we run
into in Lancaster City are speaking
another language at home. And you know,
not doesn't mean they're not speaking
English out in public, but like it's
important that we're doing this. And so
I just want to commend all the work
you're doing.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other council comments on the
resolution?
>> Comments from the public on the
as you may be the first person, you may
need just to flip it on.
>> Perfect.
>> All right. Can you hear me? Okay.
>> Yes. Thank you. Of course.
>> My name is Rachel Hellwig. I'm the
associate director for development and
engagement at Churchill Service
Lancaster. And first I would like to
echo uh council members comments in
gratitude and recognition of Zyra her
leadership and professionalism um as
well as the department of neighborhood
engagement and um the office of language
services in particular. Uh I am really
honored to get to be Zyra's colleague um
and I work with her closely. So thank
you for your leadership and for sharing
this with us tonight. At Churchold
Service Lancaster, we believe that a
thriving community is one where everyone
feels safe, valued, and supported. We
may not all speak the same languages,
but we all share a love for our families
and a desire to make our communities
better. We'd like to thank city council
and the city of Lancaster for your
ongoing commitment to building a
welcoming community where everyone feels
a sense of belonging and has the tools
they need to thrive. Resolutions like
this and the one honoring Hispanic
Heritage Month following, along with the
sustained commitment to language access,
to integrating diverse voices into city
planning and initiatives,
all show the city's commitment to a
community where everyone is welcomed and
valued for their diverse histories,
traditions, and cultures that are making
Lancaster stronger. These past nine
months have been extremely challenging
for our refugee and immigrant neighbors
as well as refugee resettlement
organizations like CWS Lancaster.
Right now, the indefinite suspension of
the US refugee resettlement program
remains largely in place, stranding
thousands of refugees who had been
conditionally approved for resettlement,
including some who were scheduled to
arrive here in Lancaster uh and rejoin
their families they had been separated
from. and sweeping changes to the US
immigration system are generating fear
among immigrant communities regardless
of visa status. We know that these
actions do not reflect our values or who
we are as a community. Welcoming is a
core part of who we are in Lancaster and
who we've always been. Although these
are challenging times, tonight's
resolution and continued commitment to
welcome demonstrates that the beauty of
Lancaster as a welcoming place where
human dignity and agency is honored and
the diversity of background is
cherished, will not be destroyed. Thank
you for your ongoing support.
Thank you very much.
Are there any further comments from the
public on the resolution?
Hearing
none. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. Med.
>> I.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Please.
>> I.
>> M. Greg.
>> Mr. Hersh.
>> I.
>> President Baker.
>> Thank you. Counselors.
And thank you to our Department of
Neighborhood Engagement.
The next item on our agenda this evening
is resolution number 57205.
Mr. Harris.
>> A resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster rec. September 15, 2025
through October 15, 2025 as Hispanic
Heritage Month and encouraging awareness
among the citizens of Lancaster of the
important contributions from people of
Latino descent. Motion to approve.
Second,
>> we have a motion and a second. Councelor
Royal.
>> Thank you, Council President. I don't
have much to add, but just uh it's truly
an honor to introduce this resolution
every year uh to honor Hispanic Heritage
Month, which begins September 15th
through October 15th. As we look around
through different community
organizations and community leaders that
are led by um Hispanic community leaders
is truly um we definitely get to see the
impact by our Hispanic community right
here in Lancaster and our community is
better for it. Um, along with the
welcoming city ordinance, the Hispanic
Heritage uh month resolution, it's just
a reminder that now more than ever, we
need to be unapologetic of celebrating
diversity, equity, and inclusion in our
home here in Lancaster City, uh,
regardless of, uh, what's happening
outside. So, um, I'm very grateful for
council to stand behind this resolution.
>> Thank you very much, Council Royo. I
will just add that at our next regular
meeting, we will have a visit from a
member of the governor's Hispanic
Heritage Month, uh, excuse me, the um,
Governor's Commission on Latino Affairs
to uh, read the governor's proclamation
for the same. Um, and I was excited to
have them join us here in Lancaster for
that. Any additional council comments on
the resolution
>> from the public?
>> Hearing none, Mr. Harris.
>> Mr.
I
>> Mr. Roy
>> I
>> Mr. Gleas
>> Mr. Greg
>> I
>> Mr. H
>> President Baker
>> I thank you very much.
>> Our next item on this part of the agenda
is resolution number 58 2025. Mr.
Harris,
>> a resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster calling on the legislature
of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania to
pass legislation to adopt Senate Bill
504, the Community Energy Act, and to
allow for the creation of community
energy programs in Pennsylvania.
>> Motion to approve. Second.
>> Have a motion and a second. Uh, this is
being introduced by Councelor Hirs.
>> Thank you, Council President. Um, this
resolution voices support for PA Senate
Bill 504, an act providing for the
creation of community energy facilities
in Pennsylvania, including community
solar facilities. Uh, this legislation
creates a regulatory framework to help
create community solar facilities in
Pennsylvania um allow electricity or
electric customers to source their power
from solar even if they do not have a
suitable roof or space for solar panels
on their own property. Um, which is many
folks here in Lancaster City. It passed
on a bipartisan vote in the Pennsylvania
State House uh by a vote of 114 ys to 89
nays and was referred to the consumer
protection and professional lensure
committee in the Pennsylvania state
senate. There are 235 proposed community
solar facilities in Pennsylvania that a
study from Penn State suggests could add
520 permanent jobs and create 83.3
million of economic activity all while
increasing green energy production here
in the Commonwealth. While we've
discussed uh been discussing issues
around energy production, climate, and
energy demand on our grid, I think it's
important that Pennsylvania passes this
legislation to increase renewable energy
production as well as increase uh the
resilience of our power grid. And um
that concludes my remarks on this
resolution.
>> Thank you very much, councelor Hirs. I
appreciate you bringing this to our
attention and the explanation that you
provided both here um and writing to
council. So, we had a full understanding
of what's been going on. Are there any
additional council comments on the
resolution
from the public?
>> Good evening.
>> You can bring that down to wherever you
need to go. And just reminder to begin
with your name and block of residence.
Thank you.
>> My name is Elizabeth Hoffman. I live in
the block of East Ros Street. And thank
you again, Councelor Hirs, for
shephering through this resolution. I'm
a member of Third Act Pennsylvania, uh,
that works on climate and democracy, and
one of our top goals is getting state
lawmakers to pass community solar for
Pennsylvania. And as we all know, energy
is getting more expensive in part
because of data centers and also we're
using more AC because the summers are
hotter. And community solar is one of
the fastest ways to get more energy on
the grid. And that can help bring down
prices uh because it doesn't have to go
through PJM that operates our um
electric grid.
Sorry.
Also, Pennsylvania ranks a really
embarrassing 49th among states in growth
of renewable energy and we get less than
1% of our energy from solar and um as
councelor Hir said a lot of people in
Maser can't have solar now because um
they're renters or the roofs are too
shady or they just can't afford it. And
with community solar a business or
farmer or a nonprofit puts up a solar
array such as on warehouse roofs, brown
fields, our farms as part of agricult.
And then the residents subscribed to the
project
with guaranteed savings. And I
subscribed to one of these in when I
lived in Maryland. And I really
appreciated both the savings and knowing
that I was helping put solar energy on
the grid. So again, thank you for
passing this resolution. We're trying to
get other municipalities to do this,
too. This morning, Pittsburgh City
Council passed it and I think tonight
Alageney County is passing it. So, thank
you very much.
>> Thank you very much. We're good company.
Any additional uh comments from the
public on the resolution
>> hearing? None. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. M.
>> I.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> I Mr. Cle.
>> Miss Greg. I
>> Mr. Hirs.
>> I President Beck. I
that will take us to the next part of
our agenda which is the first public
comment period reserved for residents
who've contacted the city clerk prior to
the meeting uh to request the
opportunity to address council. Again,
duration of comments is limited to three
minutes per speaker and please begin
with your name and block of residents.
Uh Mr. Harris, we have comments for the
first public comment period tonight.
>> We do. First is Frank Arulio.
Good evening.
>> Good evening everyone and thank you for
this opportunity to speak. Uh, I want to
particularly thank the council uh for
the resolution passed at the last
meeting requesting uh a draft to amend
the city ordinance to be more
specifically directed the the
regulations and the manner in which data
centers can be regulated through our
zoning code. Um, I know uh counselors
Ahmed and Craig were not here at the
time. Um, so they didn't get to vote on
it, but I would hope that both of you uh
are highly supportive. I would expect
that you would be of that. Um, so that's
good and that's progress. In less than
two weeks, I will be having an appeal
before the zoning hearing board
disputing the classification
uh of the data center uh as proposed. Uh
and so what did happen without telling
anyone and by anyone I mean the council,
the planning commission
uh and certainly the general public, the
administration gave
approval for two data centers by calling
those data centers warehouses.
Basically the the classification is
wholesale trade and storage which data
centers clearly are not. But having
classified them this way, it gave the
developers the right to do anything
within uh within that zoning
classification without any scrutiny
whatsoever.
So, I am faced in less than two weeks
with trying to convince the zoning
hearing board that a data center is not
a warehouse.
How in the world could I possibly do
that?
Well, I realize that I've already
answered my own question. The city
council has unanimously voted to request
an ordinance amendment that deals with
data centers specifically in their own
classification and not as warehouses. So
the city council by its action has said
and declared that data centers are not
wholesale trade and storage warehouses
and should not be regulated accordingly.
So look in your in email inbox
counselors because I'm going to send you
emails to ask you to testify as a
witness at that zoning hearing board to
to show the the board that in fact data
centers and warehouses are two different
things. I'll also ask you in that email
to sign on to the appeal along with me
and some of the other residents in the
city of Lancaster. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you very much,
Mr. Harris. We have additional
commenters for this period.
>> We do have next.
>> Thank you.
Good evening. Um I am here again this
evening regarding um
drafting the uh possible
resolution for the property located
under condemnation since 20121.
Major repairs have already been
completed and certified. Um No, no full
reinspection has ever taken place. The
community is ready to help. As um
previously mentioned in prior uh city
council um meetings,
residents like Mary Jones, Sean Carter,
Jeremy Newman, and many others are
willing to finish any remaining of the
2021 items that were listed in the
condemnation for 901 M Street. The city
keeps issuing citations at other
while 901 Manner Street remains
unresolved. This delay this delay is
affordable housing during a crisis. My
request to city council is very simple.
Either allow the community to finish any
remaining items listed in the 2021
condemnation items or have the city
complete them at cost and just film me.
Would that be simple?
then reinspect, lift the condemnation,
and restore the housing.
This property needs to be back on the uh
on the housing market in the midst of a
price of a housing crisis. Thank you.
Thank you,
Mr. Harris. Are there any further
commenters for this period?
>> No, there are not.
>> Thank you very much. We will now move to
our next item on the agenda, which is
reports requested by council. Uh this
evening we have the Lancaster Public
Library 2026 budget presentation. Um and
I will welcome you forward. Uh great.
>> Good evening and thank you for being
here.
Y there.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh I did leave some hard copies of this
presentation for any counselors or
community members uh that would like I
left it with Mr. Paris. So, councilors,
Eric Sarra, President and community
members, thank you for this chance to
share on behalf of Lancaster Public
Library. Uh we value this partnership
and we so appreciate the opportunity to
share uh each year about what's been
happening at the library and to also
make a request for the coming year.
Lancaster Public Library, which if you
don't know is just right back there, uh
our mission Oh, sorry. I'm John Heinway.
I'm the director of donor advising for
Lancaster Public Library. The whole USB
thing threw me off. uh and also a city
resident. And with me are our executive
director, Melissa Holland, and our
library manager, Karina Burns, and our
board president back there, Debbie Keys.
Um when we have a chance for questions
at the end, uh our two librarians might
answer them instead of me depending on
the question. Lancaster Public
Libraryies mission is to inspire,
empower, and strengthen our community by
connecting people with information,
ideas, and enriching experiences. and
our vision by providing equitable access
to vital educational resources,
exceptional programming, and community
building opportunities. Lancaster Public
Library is recognized as a dynamic
center and a corner of knowledge and a
cornerstone of a thriving Lancaster
community.
In our last complete year, 2024, uh here
are some stats on how city residents
used the library. nearly 50% uh 46% of
city residents are library card holders
which is really cool. Uh over 156,000
materials were borrowed by city
residents within the year. And to give
an idea of the value of those free
resources for the community. That is
$4.5 million in free resources that our
community access within one year. And
that's just the materials that are
checked out. that doesn't include uh
things like being able to come in and
use Wi-Fi, attending programs, and the
many other valuable resources that
people access through the library.
And beyond Lancaster City, uh uh all the
the work that we're doing in the broader
community, uh we had over 236,000
patron visits to the library. Over half
a million items were circulated uh to
members of the community. And one of the
most vital uh resources that is offered
is uh access to internet um and uh and
devices which as we all know if we're
paying for devices and or internet at
home is expensive. Uh and so that is an
incredible thing for people to access
and we had over 80,000 uh connections to
either our public computers or uh to the
free wireless internet.
We offer a lot of things beyond just
books uh which you're probably familiar
with but if you're not um here are some
examples and I won't go through all of
them in detail but a few that I want to
highlight our business and reference
center uh is a really exceptional
resource and unique not only to the
county but in the surrounding counties
uh the types of uh databases and other
resources that are available through
that um are the sorts of things that
programs like SCORE the business
mentoring program they send clients to
come utilize those resources and we get
people from uh well beyond Lancaster to
uh access that. Um the autism resource
center is one that we would love for the
community to become more aware of uh
resources specifically for individuals
or families uh who have someone uh who
who is on the autism spectrum or has
other uh a different sensory disorder.
Um I mentioned some of the the internet
pieces. Another one I want to call out
is our work rooms and meeting rooms and
those are available for rent which is a
revenue stream for us but also we have a
flex office which is a small meeting
room there that is available for
nonprofits to use for free um to meet
with clients. So I want you as leaders
in the community and community members
to be aware of that. We would love to
see that continue to be utilized even
more. Um, and along with the programs
and uh lots of fun items that can be
checked out like uh I've checked out the
parachute for our neighborhood night
out, things like that. Um, another one
is our e- resources. A lot of people are
familiar with Libya and Hoopla. So
there's ebooks, audiobooks, uh,
streaming, all sorts of things. Again,
stuff that is very expensive if you're
doing it by a subscription, free to
access for the community. And I
specifically want to call out load for
kids uh which is a new resource that we
added just this year as we've been and I
appreciated the language access uh
presentation uh as we have been working
at language access as well. It's very
hard to get children's books in the many
different languages represented in our
community and this digital resource is
an amazing tool. Uh it has dozens and
dozens of different languages,
children's books that are uh available
both you you can they're digitally
either to read or as audio books and uh
one of our uh new neighbors uh friends,
a family from Afghanistan that joined
the community this year, I sat down with
them and was looking at this and they
were able to uh play one of these
children's books alternating between
English and I forget which of their home
languages. They have several uh uh that
they their family speaks. uh one of
their languages, we were able to
alternate it between English and their
uh their language of their home and it's
an amazing resource for families,
children to learn English, but also for
adults uh to be able to learn English.
So, I want people to know about that and
please do spread the word about that as
we partner with the city on uh on
language access and being a welcoming
city.
We have continued to see uh increase in
our program attendance. In 2024, we saw
an 18% increase in attendance at our
programs. We just came off of our summer
reading for 2025. Over 4,000 uh
community members participated and uh we
offered over 200 programs and over a
thousand of the summer reading
challenges were completed uh which was
really cool. Um, a few of the new
programs and there are many more, but
some of the highlights uh that were
added that were new last year, read it
and eat it cookbook club has been very
popular. Uh, we did our first fully ASL
story time. We also did our fully our
first fully Spanish story time. Uh, and
we added a future architects club and uh
there's a lot of popular programs. A few
are baby story time which keeps having a
lot of people come out to it. And that
one is really special because especially
for new parents who have had their first
child and are looking for community and
connection, many people form
relationships and find support coming to
that baby story time which is really
special. Uh and many other uh clubs and
uh and book clubs and programs that we
have as well.
In terms of our funding, um we broke it
out a little bit more in this one than
we have in previous presentations. 64%
of our um our revenue is generated by
the library and 36 comes 36% comes from
government sources. Uh significantly
over 7% is through ARPA funding which
the city has been an amazing partner on
and that will extend through 2026. After
that one of the things we're looking at
is how do we build sustainable funding
uh as that uh as that goes away. Um,
we're very grateful to the
municipalities like Lancaster City who
support us financially. Uh, that's about
9%. Um, and fundraising between the work
that, uh, my department does and our
friends, volunteers, uh, makes up about
50% of our budget. So, amazing community
support that we're very, very grateful
for, uh, and is vital to our ability to
continue offering these services to the
community.
While the national average for uh
support for libraries from local
municipalities is much higher because of
the way that Pennsylvania is structured,
it's a little bit different.
Pennsylvania recommends $5 per capita um
from local municipalities for funding.
We average among the 14 municipalities
that we're responsible for serving $1
per capita. Uh Lancaster, thank you. Uh
you are above that average uh pushing $2
per capita and we're very very grateful
for that. Um, I'll get into that a
little bit more in a in a later slide
here.
We are the eighth largest service area
within the state of Pennsylvania of 450
libraries. And uh to show how amazing
this resource is for our community, we
have the 18th largest catalog of
materials among the libraries in
Pennsylvania. And this is just Lancaster
Public Library. This is not the
countywide system. All the libraries
included. just uh uh downtown and the
Mount Bill branch. So really a lot of
wonderful things for our community to
access.
We are incredibly appreciative of the
city of Lancaster uh and the financial
support that we have received and
faithful uh generous partnership over
many years and especially as we uh came
into this year and the question of home
rule and all of that the various budget
scenarios. We knew that it may not play
out this way and we are so grateful uh
for uh that ongoing support at 110,000
again this year. Um
and we do hope that you will consider uh
at least that again moving into next
year. Um and we are again very grateful
for the support through ARPA as well.
And later on tonight we will make the
presentation on the lang the local share
account grant that we'll be applying for
uh with the city. Um but we do encourage
you to consider continuing to increase
as our costs are going up. uh if we did
get $5 per capita from the 14
municipalities that we serve, it would
be $1.1 million, which is nearly half of
our annual budget. So, if each of those
municipalities continues to push uh up
that amount that is being given, uh the
way that we'll be able to serve the
community will will really grow.
Additionally, I mentioned the support of
our community uh in the last five years.
So recent and active donors uh 782
individual community members have given
to Lancaster Public Library and uh
businesses and other community
organizations 74 uh different ones over
that time. So we do really applaud and
express our gratitude to our incredibly
generous community.
So what's next and what are our dreams
especially as we do grow our funding and
our sustainability
uh through the ARPA funding we have
added our onthe-go mobile library which
we are incredibly excited about. Uh this
is an incredible step for us and uh Lisa
as director for these past years has
wanted to really work at uh overcoming
barriers in our community and making
sure that everyone in our community can
access the resources of the library and
taking away mobility issues and language
access issues, awareness, all sorts of
things.
So this year we launched this. We have a
full-time uh outreach specialist and a
new van that's pictured there in the
corner uh that is getting out uh went on
uh Tuesdays in the park uh rotated to
the different city parks over the summer
and partnering with schools and other
community programs. Uh 42 community
organizations already have been
partnered with and over 5,000 community
members have had interactions with this
mobile library. So, we're very excited
to be offering that and to grow that and
grow our partnerships
as we can increase our funding. Some of
the things that we hope to do are expand
those community partnerships even more
and capitalize on uh that new program
that we have launched. We want to grow
our ASL, Spanish, and other community
language offerings uh so that we better
represent the community and serve our
community in all of its diversity. We
would love to extend our evening hours
for uh working professionals that find
it hard to get into the library during
our hours. We would love to hire a
social worker to support our patrons in
uh additional ways. And we would love to
have uh more staff presence out on the
floor to uh take the initiative in
approaching and supporting patrons in
whatever they might need.
There is a QR code on there that goes to
our website, not to our donation page,
but you can get there from that. Um and
uh there is my contact information as
well and uh yeah welcome any questions
and again uh Lisa or Karina might join
me in answering any questions.
>> Thank you so much for your presentation
this evening. Um I do have a question
off the bat. So having seen you know
these presentations for now several
years it seems sort of anecdotally if
I'm remembering correctly that your
participation has gone up since your new
location. Could someone uh speak to the
way that things have changed like
daytoday in the library since it moved
to its new location? Um the good, the
the bad, the the positive. What how much
how much would you say has increased
since the new location opened?
>> Come on.
Don't be shy.
Thank you.
Definitely one of the things we've seen
for sure is um people just coming and
enjoying the space. It's a lot more open
to people who are there to um just relax
and read or work with their iPads or
their laptops. It's it's just a much
more open inviting space. Um we have
more computer access than we did at the
old building. Uh it's a much more open
area also for computers and we have 16
public computers and they are well used
very very well used. Um we have the
terrace area now which is wonderful. We
never had anything like that before and
people are definitely enjoying that
during the summer.
Um as far as our uh children's area that
has really picked up. We divided out our
children and our teen sections. That was
huge in this building and you know we've
seen the differences there. We are able
to really focus more on teens now and um
we can really do some of the great
programming that brings them in like
anime club and teen gaming and so that's
been fantastic. Um the
attendance at our like our baby story
time that John was talking about we
doubled that. We had one in the old
building. Now we have it twice on a
Tuesday because we had so many babies
who wanted to come to baby story time
and of course their parents do. Um and
so that has grown. Our summer reading um
is growing. We
went downhill with that after 2020, but
that is starting to pick up again. And I
think moving into the new building,
having um more accessibility to outdoor
programming. We've been doing a lot of
things at Muser Park and out in the
plaza has grown some numbers there as
well for summer readings. So, we're
getting back to where we were before.
So, really overall there are just
meeting spaces that's so much better
than um in the old building we had one
auditorium that we shared for children,
teens, tween, adults, and now we have
three or four spaces and we can do more
programs at the same time. So now we
sometimes have two adult programs going
on at the same time because we have two
rooms with a wall in between and we can
also have one or two children's programs
going on upstairs at the same time. So
we can just do more programming each
day. We can get more programming in. So
lots and lots of benefits as far as the
space and the community gathering that
we have in the building. Thank you so
much.
It's um it's always nice to hear about
opportunities for spaces where people
can just exist without the expectation
to spend any money uh because we don't
have any of those besides the library
and that's why it's so valuable. So,
thank you for that.
>> Counselors, uh any questions or comments
on the presentation this evening?
>> Thank you so much for joining us this
evening.
>> I would just quickly add one other piece
in answer to that question too. uh is
that I think being on Ule Plaza and all
of the community events that are
happening in Ule Plaza and Bins Park is
growing awareness in the community of
the library because it's right there. Um
and other than a couple I started with
the library less than two years ago. So
in the new building, uh other than
taking my nieces and nephews to check
out books, my only other time in the
library before I went to interview was I
had to go to the bathroom when I was at
the Hispanic Heritage Festival. So I
went in. So, I really do think that that
partnership as well and like some
intentionality that uh we've had between
the city and the library that I think we
can continue to grow has really given
opportunities for people to to become
familiar with the library or to be
reminded of it to get into it and see
the new the new space and then access
resources.
>> I agree. Thank you for being an anchor
in that public space for us.
Yes.
As you may remember, we had a little
incident last March with uh story hour
and I want to say that although it was
horrible as we went through it, it has
brought the staff together. The silver
lining is we all realized what the
mission and vision were and work very
hard now to stay within that and to be
welcoming and really thinking through
every new program or any new policy that
it doesn't put up any kinds of barriers.
And that is something that I want to
commend the staff on for for doing. So
um
in all bad things something good comes
out of and that was what was good out of
it and it's how we have progressed in
the last year and a half just to be who
we are and welcoming to everybody.
>> Thank you so much.
Appreciate you coming and joining us
this evening.
>> Thank you. Thanks for the opportunity
and thank you again for your support and
partnership.
>> We'll take a moment to reset tech before
we continue.
All right.
As we are getting reset, we'll move to
our next item on the agenda, which is
reports of committees of council. These
are the meetings that were held on
September 2nd, 2025. Uh first is our
public safety committee. Um in council
Diaz's absence, uh council hir, would
you mind reviewing the work of the
public safety committee?
>> Yes, the public safety committee met and
heard um one item and one item was uh
tabled. Uh the item that was heard will
be heard later on the legislative agenda
resolution 59 adopting the Lancaster
County Hazard Mitigation Plan.
>> Thank you very much. And I will continue
with you, Council Hirs, and the Public
Works Committee.
>> Uh the public works committee did not
meet.
>> Thank you. Economic Development
Committee, Councelor Med.
>> Uh thank you, council president. The
economic development committee did not
meet.
>> You finance committee councelor Royo.
>> Thank you, council president. The
finance committee did meet. We discussed
bill number 6 2025 uh which authorized
issuance of a $32 million gener general
obligation note. Uh this is for the 42
in uh water transmission line
replacement. Uh the total project is for
$41 million, but this uh interim
financing would only be for $32 million
to ensure that the project is shovel
ready and so we can secure long-term
financing from Penvest. That concludes
my report. Council President,
>> thank you very much. Community Planning
Committee. Councelor Craig.
>> Thank you, Council President. Um,
community planning did meet. We had five
items on the agenda.
All
five women.
No, four of which will come up on our
legislative agenda.
>> Thank you very much. And personnel
committee councelor Kix.
>> Thank you, Madame President. Uh the
personal committee did meet uh on
September 2nd and review nominations for
reappointment to the public art advisory
board and sewer appeals board. That
concludes my report. Madame President,
>> thank you very much. That takes us to
our legislative agenda this evening. Uh
we begin with those nominations for
appointment. Councelor Glee.
>> Thank you, Madam President. I make a
motion to reappoint Kesha Finny to the
public art advisory board for a term
from July 31st, 2025 to July 31st, 2027.
And Steven Campbell to the sewer appeals
board for a term from September 12, 2025
to September 12th, 2030.
>> Second.
>> Thank you. We have a motion and a second
for our nominations. Are there any
councilor comments on them?
Comments from the public on the
nominations.
>> Good evening.
>> Hello. Tony Dash of 700 block and New
Holland Avenue. Uh I actually think both
of these nominations should go forward.
I just want to point out an
inconsistency in logic which is that we
have a board here that's strictly
advisory.
So we're having conversations about
other entities and I'm coming to say
that advisory bodies are important
bodies uh just because they don't have
any
we'll we'll say power in a conventional
sense they do have power. They're
educational. They help you have inter
wow interface with the people you need
to talk to. Advisory bodies are
important.
So we as a city really shouldn't be
discussing matters for the public and
saying that just because something is
not empowered to for example discipline
or take action against it doesn't mean
it doesn't have value.
Thank you.
>> Any additional comments from the public
on the nominations?
Hearing
none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. M.
>> I.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> Mr. Cle.
>> I.
>> M. Craig.
>> Mr. Hersh.
>> Hi.
>> President Baker.
>> I.
>> Next item on the agenda this evening are
items for the heritage conservation and
historic districts. Mr. Harris.
>> Yes, Madam President. Uh, considering
the following application applications
recommendation from the commission and
historical architectural review board
for improvements to properties within
the heritage conservation district and
historic districts. Peter and Kula
Vasquez, owners of 53 North Water
Street, proposed demolition of a
one-story two bay cement block garage to
create service parking. That was
recommended for approval by the
historical commission. And Community
Fellowship Church, owner of 344 West
Chestnut Street, requests installation
of a new projecting sign on the
building's west elevation facing North
Charlotte Street. And that application
was recommended for approval by the
historical architectural review board.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion on a second. Councelor
Craig. Anything additional on those two
items?
>> Honestly, nothing more than what was
said in the resolution. Um the
344 West Chestnut Street is I think one
of the things that we point out is that
the
the west elevation facing north, it's
going to be mounted on the west
elevation point facing North Charlotte
Street
per the submitted plan stipulating that
the sign be mounted within the mortar
joints, not directly into the stone. So,
nothing more than than that.
>> Thank you very much, Councelor Craig.
And both of those were um recommended
for our approval. Any additional council
comments on the applications
comments from the public or the
applicants? There
>> hearing none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. M. I
>> Mr. Royal I.
>> Mr. Cle,
>> Miss Gray, I
>> Mr. H. I present Baker.
>> I
Next item are ordinances for first
reading. We have administration bill
number 7, 2025. Mr. Harris,
>> an ordinance of the council of the city
of Lancaster, County of Lancaster,
Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, adopting a
five-year capital plan for the fiscal
years of 2026 to 2030. A program
providing for the proper acquisition,
repair, and provision for the necessary
equipment and infrastructure for the
effective and efficient delivery of
public services, including projects
resulting in the additions,
replacements, or changes to city
facilities, infrastructure, and
equipment. Allowing for a severance
provision, providing for the repeal of
inconsistent ordinances, and providing
for an effective date.
>> Motion to approve. Second,
>> this is a first reading this evening,
but good job everyone. We were on the
ball.
>> That's right.
>> So, this item is for first reading. We
have had the capital budget presented to
us several times. Uh, council Royo,
anything to add this evening?
>> Nothing to add and maybe, well, excuse
me, one thing to add.
>> Thank you. Uh and maybe director
Campbell could provide clarification,
but uh there may this may not be uh
approved at the next uh meeting until we
receive quotes for the interest rates, I
believe, or
no,
>> this one should be approved at the next
meeting. Um the the water main financing
will be the first reading will be next
meeting. So that one
>> confusing all the financing ones. Thank
you, Director Campbell.
>> Thank you. And I just want to say to
Director Campbell and uh Director Steven
Campbell as well, because I know they've
worked closely together on this, that
I'm incredibly proud that we have this
capital budget in front of us. Um it's
really it's kind of a momentous thing
and um I'm I'm glad that we're doing it
because it shows a level of fiscal
responsibility that I think that other
cities um could learn from. Um and a
fact the fact that we are being u
responsible stewards to our tax dollars
and making a plan five years out for
these incredibly expensive and
complicated infrastructure pro uh
projects uh speaks volumes to the
planning that goes into our uh
department of public works and our
administrative services budget as well.
So thank you for all the work that
you've put into this.
Additional comments from council on the
first reading.
comments from the public on the first
reading.
Okay, hearing none, I will thank
everyone and we will uh be voting on
this at our next meeting. So, thank you.
>> Next item on the agenda this evening is
resolutions. We will begin with
administration resolution number 59205.
Mr. Harris.
>> A resolution of the city council of the
city of Lancaster adopting the 2025
Lancaster County Hazard Mitigation Plan.
>> Motion to approve. Second.
>> We have a motion and a second. Um, in
lie of councelor Diaz, councelor Hirs,
would you please review this one this
for us this evening?
>> Yes. Um so resolution 59 adopts the 2025
hazard mitigation plan um from or the
Lancaster County hazard mitigation plan
adopted by county government and then
subsequently by uh the participating
municipalities in order to be eligible
for post- disaster relief funding for
the disaster mitigation act of 2000. Um,
at our committee meeting on September
2nd, we heard from Deputy Fire Chief
Christa Long, who along with other
representatives from Lancaster City
worked with county government on the
updates made to this plan. Original plan
was written um in 2019, and this uh
addresses um hazards, both natural and
humanmade, uh, and how to respond to
them were they to occur. And the plan's
very thorough. It's 674 pages long. Um,
so some light reading for for y'all.
Thank you very much, councelor Hirs. Any
additional comments from council on the
resolution
from the public?
>> Hear none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Men,
>> I Mr. Royal
>> I.
>> Mr. Cle,
>> Miss Craig,
>> I
>> Mr. Hish
>> I.
>> President B.
The next item is resolution number 60
2025. Mr.
A resolution to the council of the city
of Lancaster approving an amended
easement agreement between the city of
Lancaster and Her Arcade Condominium
Association granting an amended easement
to Hagar Arcade for encroachments into
the public right away over under and
within North Market Street and West
Grant Street as more fully set forth in
the amended amended easement agreement.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second. Have a motion and a second.
Councelor Craig.
>> Thank you, Council President. Um um
this was originally um
the original res resolution
we went over in May. The amendment is
because of a of an incorrectly listed
height measurement from 15t to 13t 6 in
which um complies with the city's
ordinances. So just a slight error in
measurement that was corrected.
>> Thank you very much councelor Craig. Any
additional comments from council on the
resolution
from the public? Hear
none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Met I,
>> Mr. Roar,
>> I,
>> Mr. Gleas,
>> Miss Greg,
>> I,
>> Mr. Hersh,
>> the president
>> I,
>> the next two resolutions that we have in
front of us are application authorizing
applications to the local shares account
program. Uh, I don't know if Director
Campbell, you wanted to add any context
before we begin to hear these this
evening for council other members of the
public or I'm happy to. We've done these
a couple of years in a row. I'll just
remind members of council and the public
that these applications to our local
shares account are actually applications
for funding at the state level. They
need to be authorized by the
municipality. So, we will hear them and
uh treat them as resolutions to vote on.
Uh but the funding is not coming from
the city of Lancaster for the projects
that we're about to hear about. So uh we
begin with resolution number 62205.
Uh Mr. Harris,
>> I'm sorry. Resolution 61.
>> Oh, I'm so sorry. I was I was there and
then I I scrolled. Resolution 61 2025.
Mr.
A resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster authorizing the filing of
the Commonwealth Finance Finance
Authority local share account
application for funding in the amount
not to exceed $1 million for Lancaster
Public Libraryies book resort
sustainability project.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> A motion and a second. I will welcome
our representatives from the Lancaster
Public Library to speak to their local
shares account application.
Welcome back.
>> Thank you. Still John Heinley, still
director of donor advising at Langster
Public Library.
>> You got a two for tonight.
>> Uh I'll read through the proposal that's
been submitted and want to thank city
staff uh especially Jen for uh support
in this whole process.
Uh yeah, local shares account funding
for the book resort sustainability
project would allow Lancaster Public
Library to purchase and renovate the
property at 225 North Marshall Street.
uh completing key renovations to update
that building. The project's anticipated
budget breakdown includes 750,000 for
the purchase uh which uh slight
adjustment to the wording that you
received uh does not include the closing
costs. So 750,000 plus closing costs uh
and then uh 20,000 for administrative
fees and the remaining hopefully 200 or
more thousand for renovations.
renovations uh would be prioritized with
probably uh the HBAC system, the
electrical and roofing to be prioritized
uh based on the budget for each of those
items. The friends of Lancaster Public
Library, which is a volunteer group, um
currently leases the book resource
facility at 225 North Marshall Street.
It's a volunteer-run operation that
sorts and sells gently used books
through the Marshall Street bookstore,
Juliana Bookstore, which is the at the
downtown branch online and at annual
events uh like the big book sale and a
smaller one on site next weekend if
anyone's interested. Uh and uh so the um
the yeah the big book sale which just
celebrated its 70th anniversary. Uh so
an incredible uh history there. The
facility is ideally suited to its
purpose with a storefront and sufficient
warehouse space to house and process the
200 over 250,000 books and materials
that are included annually in the big
big book sale as well as other sales
throughout the year. The adjoining
parking lot which has the same owner and
is leased by horse in provides crucial
access for volunteer and customer
parking and for the flow of traffic for
community members to drop off their book
donations.
uh ownership would uh protect this vital
revenue generating operation that
contributes over $200,000 annually uh to
the library and continued rental income
from Horson's lease uh and uh there's
desire on both sides of this to continue
that partnership uh would also help with
the financial sustainability. So yeah,
we appreciate the support with this. It
is it's an incredible community
resource. We have a lot of people who
volunteer and the volunteers have
wonderful community amongst themselves.
Um, and the sales offer a really great
opportunity for the community to access
uh affordable books. Not quite as
affordable as literally checking them
out at the library, but lowcost books
that people can own, which is a really
special resource to the community and it
is uh a very important financial support
to the library every year uh doing all
the wonderful things that we talked
about earlier. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much. a question for you.
Uh, one, first, thank you for answering
the important question was that is the
horse end still going to be able to park
there? So, thank you. Um, and two, I
guess I did not realize that the
facility wasn't already owned by the
library. So, who are the owners
currently, if you would not mind
disclosing?
>> Yeah, Al Medbed.
>> Okay.
>> Uh, and he uh he has expressed the
desire for the library and for Horse In
both of which are uh have a long history
with the the family. uh the desire for
both the library and uh horse end to
continue to be able to have uh those
facilities um and the family as well as
uh on board with that. So all parties
are excited about this.
>> That's great to hear. Thank you. Uh any
additional comments or questions from
council?
>> Councelor Clees.
>> Thank you, Madam President. Thank you
for the presentation. And I was
wondering how the library measure uh
measures um the success of its projects.
For example, how they measure the the
you can say if the investments are
paying off. So how does the library
measures
>> like for this facility specifically or
the other like the programming?
>> The the program.
>> Oh the programming. Um yeah. So, we are
required by the state, and Lisa can
speak to this if I miss anything. Uh,
we're required by the state to measure a
whole bunch of different metrics that
we're submitting on a monthly and annual
basis. Uh, and that does include the the
amount of items that are circulating.
Uh, it includes the access to public
computers and, uh, wireless sessions,
attendance at programs, uh, all sorts of
things like that. So, um, a lot of what
we're measuring is really related to the
community usage and, uh, how that
compares year-to-year, um, when we're
looking at our own work and how that
compares as well to, uh, other libraries
within Lancaster County and peer
libraries, uh, throughout the state
would give us kind of a gauge for that.
Um, but also community feedback, I would
say, is really vital to that. Uh and so
um yeah, some of the things like uh uh
with the Spanish story times, ASL story
times that we've added, the the evident
desire for that and the way that that
meets needs in the community, the
feedback that back that we have gotten
on those sorts of things tells us that
uh that adding those accessibility and
uh diversity components so that we are
able to reach more of our community in
more meaningful ways. Uh that that that
says a lot to us about uh what we're
doing. anything you would add?
>> I would make it very simple and say
numbers of attendees and um the feedback
from the community. Our programming has
jumped year after year since we've
moved. So that's three years. But it we
are keeping the programs that the um
community comes come and and participate
in and after a while we let go of
programs that have run their course or
were not something that the community
needed. So we have a very close
relationship to what their needs are and
what we will provide the best we can.
>> Thank you. We've als we've also
increased the uh grant funding that
we've received from different sources
which has been helpful as well to uh
there's of course different things that
they're looking for us to report on. uh
and so that has increased the number of
things that we're tracking that are
actually helpful metrics for us as well
in addition to the state required
metrics.
>> Uh how does the how how do these funds
benefit for example working families,
students, seniors
>> in a variety of ways. um again coming in
and using um technology for free. When
we were in the building that was across
the street, we had 12 public computers
and maybe in the last year that we were
there, there were people, one or two
people at them. Immediately upon moving,
we have 16 that are always always busy.
So that's one way Um, our program
attendance for adults is growing. Um,
for the business center, we have every
person that goes through the score
program is sent to the library and we
have people from Dolphin and York
counties coming and using those
facilities because the databases are
very expensive for an individual to buy
or to and to I guess rent or whatever.
But um so that's a way that we know that
we are reaching people. Um the feedback
from a baby story time literally it is
almost out of control. At one point we
had 36 babies at one story time. That's
why we divided it up and that's why we
give the opportunity that if your baby
sleeps in the morning, you might want to
come at in the afternoon and vice versa.
Um and the feedback from the
organizations that we are partnering
with too, they're seeing an increase in
um number of people taking part in the
programs that they too are providing and
that we are hosting.
>> Those those partnerships would be one of
the things I would highlight too that
has increased with the new location
because of the space we have available.
were able to partner even more with
different organizations and there's many
but uh like Career Link um uh uh Penn
State nurses would come in and offer
resources and so a big part of it is
being a resource hub. We're not we're
not the experts. We're not offering the
service itself necessarily, but making
the space where people know they can
come to access all sorts of resources is
a big part of what we're doing.
>> Thank you. Thank you so much. I would
also say the increase in donor support
too. If we weren't doing something that
they wanted, I don't think we would get
the amount of money that we got in the
in 2024 for the support of the work we
do.
>> Thank you. Good point.
>> Thank you.
>> Additional comments from council on the
application the resolution
from the public on the resolution. Hear
none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. M.
>> I. Mr. Royer.
>> I.
>> Mr. Please.
>> M.
>> I.
>> Mr. H.
>> President Baker.
>> I. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
>> Our next item, another local shares
account uh application authorization is
resolution number 62 2025. Mr.
A resolution of the council of the city
of Lancaster authorizing the filing of
the Commonwealth Finance Finance
Authority local share account
application for funding in the amount
not to exceed $1 million for Ankor
Lancaster's day shelter renovations at
10fold.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second. Uh are the
applicants from Ankor Lancaster here
this evening? No.
>> Oh, that's right. Thank you. I apologize
for that. So, councilors, we did hear
presentation from Anker Lancaster at our
last uh meeting. Are there any
additional comments on the application
from council?
>> Council Craig,
>> just I just want to mention the
incredible work that Anchor Lancaster
does as far as their services for um
homeless folks in the community. It's
incredible.
>> Thank you very much. Any comments from
the public on the resolution
hearing? None. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. M.
>> I.
>> Mr. Royer.
>> Mr. Cle.
>> I.
>> Miss. Craig.
>> Mr. Hersh.
>> I.
>> President Victor.
And as a reminder, as I mentioned at the
top of the meeting, resolution number
63, which is a similar application by
HTC Mid-Atlantic, uh will be heard at
our next meeting on the 23rd. So that
takes us then to our second public
comment period, which is open for uh for
items not on the agenda. Duration of
comments is limited to three minutes per
speaker. Please begin with your name and
block of residence. There's anyone
wishing to make comment during this
period, please proceed to the microphone
at this time.
Good evening,
>> Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland
Avenue.
Uh, to be very frank, I'm not feeling my
best right now. U,
but I'm going to paraphrase something I
hear weekly that keeps me moving. I know
one of you knows where this comes from.
I won't give up, shut up, let up. I must
go till they come, teach till I drop,
preach till I'll know, and work till
they stop me. My body's trying to stop
me right now, but I'm not going to allow
that to hold me up whenever I can.
The public library deserves the full $5
recommended by the state, if not more.
I understand.
why
certain programming has been avoided for
the moment.
We are living in a time
where people are coming for frankly our
lives in whatever aspect they can find.
I've had people ask me over the last
week what we can do for for trans
individuals in our community.
And I've also seen in response to some
of the past programming people
threatening to pull their
frankly very minor contributions to the
library.
The library needs to be as funded, as
well funded as possible
so that they can continue providing the
programming that makes will feel seen
and welcome in this community
because when we're only giving them
something that they like,
like I said, I'm not I'm not feeling my
best and I'm really not trying to crash
out on y'all right now. Really not.
This is a time where a lot of us are
worried about what might come.
But you do not light a candle and put it
under a bowl.
We have to be a beacon for people to
feel safe and comfortable amidst this
tumultuous situation not just our city,
our county, our state, our country is
finding ourselves in, if not the world.
So whatever happens,
please give the library their $5 per
capita.
Please.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Are there any further commenters for
this period?
Hearing none, we'll close the second
public comment period this evening and
thank you for that. Uh we now move to
the report of the mayor. Mayor Sarra,
>> thank you, Council President. Um
tonight, I'd like to share a few updates
on the city's permitting process. Uh
city staff across departments have been
working hard to improve the permit
process from top to bottom, making
faster, clear, and ultimately fully
online. Um, council is probably aware,
but for the public, uh, we, uh, process
permits for many different things. Um,
special events, um, renting out our
pavilions, um, uh, our fire marshals,
uh, related to, um, permitting, um, fire
suppression systems. Uh, of course,
building permits are the most common.
Uh, and In 2024, the city issued 2315
building permits and as of July 31st,
2025, we've already issued uh 1,232
and that's just uh building permits. So,
while um we have made real progress,
there's still a lot more to do relating
to our permitting. Uh staff have
developed a new system to track permits
across departments, including an
internal dashboard to make the process
easier to follow. and processing times
have also been significantly reduced. Uh
the city recently hired a new permit
coordinator. Her name is Kelly. And um
many of you know James um who now serves
as the bureau chief of building codes.
Uh the permit coordinator role also
serves as the main point of contact for
building permits, helping to move them
through the process and resolve any
holdups. In the coming weeks, a site
plan will be required for all exterior
permits to expedite the review process.
And additionally, all commercial
drawings and plans will move to online
submission only. And we're preparing for
all permits to go online in 2026 using a
platform called City View.
We've launched a permit finder tool. I
want to uh give a shout out to uh DJ
Ramsey and Wyatt Binger uh for their
work as well as many departments to
assist in developing this uh
permitfinder tool which is now available
at uh city of lancasterpa.go.
/permits. This educational tool allows
residents, business owners, and
contractors to select the type of
project they're planning and to see
which permits may be required, uh which
um will hopefully uh provide better
customer service and more thorough
permitting
for the projects that are coming in into
uh city hall. And that concludes my
report, Council President. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much for those updates,
Mayor Sarra. It's appreciated those
efforts. Um the next item on the agenda
is the report of president of council. I
do not have um a formal report to give
this evening. So we'll move to council
comments. Are there any council comments
this evening?
Then hearing none and having reached the
end of our agenda, I I'll hear a motion
to adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn.
>> Second. A
>> motion and a second. All in favor? I
>> I thank you. We're adjourned.